<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>adventuresinteach.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://www.adventuresinteach.com/</link>
   <description></description>
   <language>en-uk </language>
   <managingEditor> Jaqueline Steiger</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Discourse Markers</title>
	  <link>//discourse-markers</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-28T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//discourse-markers</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h3 id="meta-language">Meta-language</h3>

<p>We have a whole secret category of words that don’t have any semantic meaning. They don’t add to the sentence, they don’t impart any specific meaning regarding the intent of the speaker or writer. The only thing they do is provide information about the STRUCTURE of the sentence/phrase/speech (utterance) itself. We call these <strong>discourse markers</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="what-do-discourse-markers-do">What Do Discourse Markers Do?</h3>

<p>They help us organize the flow of information. We can use them to:</p>

<p>1) Signpost logical relationships and sequences - “firstly” “furthermore”, etc</p>

<p>2) Manage conversation and turn-takeing - “and you?”</p>

<p>3) Influence how our listeners or readers react - “all the same”</p>

<p>4) Express our attitude to what we say and write - “I’m afraid”</p>

<p>This is really more of a feeling than a hard and fast category. There’s not a whole lot of consensus or rigidly-defined list of discourse markers. Here are some examples:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Firstly</p>

  <p>in fact</p>

  <p>on the contrary</p>

  <p>however</p>

  <p>nevertheless</p>

  <p>futhermore</p>

  <p>right?</p>

  <p>you know</p>

  <p>on the other hand</p>

  <p>so</p>

  <p>anyway</p>

  <p>uhh</p>

  <p>finally</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All of these words/utterances tell us information about the discourse preceding or following it. How does it relate? Where is it in a sequence? How do we feel about it?</p>

<p>Things that discourse markers can do:</p>

<p>a) numbering and order</p>

<p>b) adding something</p>

<p>c) linking similar things together</p>

<p>d) introducing something that contrasts with expectations</p>

<p>e) causes and results</p>

<p>f) generalizing</p>

<p>g) exemplifying and narrowing down</p>

<p>h) re-stating</p>

<p>i) rounding off</p>

<p>j) conversation management</p>

<p>How do we teach something as subjective, varied, and intricate as discourse markers?</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Classifying Consonants</title>
	  <link>//classifying-consonants</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-26T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//classifying-consonants</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="how-do-we-distinguish-consonants">How Do We Distinguish Consonants?</h2>

<h3 id="voicing">Voicing</h3>

<p>Consonants can either be voiced or voiceless, and English comes with paired voiced and voiceless consonants: /p/ <strong>/b/</strong>, /t/ <strong>/d/</strong>, /k/ <strong>/g/</strong>, etc.</p>

<p>Note that English does not distinguish between aspirated and unaspirated consonants (<strong>aspirated</strong> = a puff of air accompanies the sound as it comes out of your mouth. Put your hand up to your mouth and say “pot” and “spot”. You’ll feel air come out for “pot” but not “spot”) but many other languages do.</p>

<h3 id="place-of-articulation">Place of Articulation</h3>

<p>We talk about consonants based on where in the mouth the airflow is restricted. Consonants that involve the lips are <em>labial</em> or <em>bilabial</em>. Consonants that involve a curled-back tongue are <em>retroflex</em>.</p>

<p>Generally, the places of articulation (FOR ENGLISH) as we move back through the mouth are thus: bilabial, labiodental, alveolar, alveopalatal, velar, glottal.</p>

<p>Fascinating types of sound we don’t have in English: retroflex, palatal, uvular, pharyngeal.</p>

<h3 id="manner-of-articulation">Manner of Articulation</h3>

<p>This variable describes the <em>way</em> in which airflow is constricted.</p>

<p><u>Stops</u> or <u>plosives</u> involve a complete blockage of airflow.</p>

<p><u>Fricatives</u> involve a narrowing of the airways and generally a hissing sound.</p>

<p><u>Nasals</u> involve air moving through the nose as well as the mouth.</p>

<p>There’s a lot of types, some of them are really interesting!</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Vowel Characteristics</title>
	  <link>//vowel-characteristics</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-24T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//vowel-characteristics</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="vowels-and-their-nonsense">Vowels and Their Nonsense</h2>

<p>One of the books I’m reading for my DELTA course is on phonetics, phonology, and the sounds of the English language. Having a linguistics degree and spending roughly a billion hours on this stuff already, it’s obvious that I am very excited to read this book.</p>

<p>For some reason, instead of starting with the easier parts of phonetics (consonants), we’re instead starting with the terror of all phonetics students, the <strong>dreaded vowels</strong>. Why are they terrible? We’ll get to that. First, let’s see what my book has to say about what vowels are/what they do/how we categorize them.</p>

<h3 id="vowels-are-sounds-made-with-no-obstruction-of-the-airflow-they-are-always-voiced">Vowels are sounds made with no obstruction of the airflow. They are always voiced.</h3>

<p>Essentially, if your mouth is open the entire time you’re making a sound, and your tongue isn’t touching any part of your mouth, and if your vocal cords are vibrating, it’s a vowel.</p>

<p>We distinguish vowels in four ways:</p>

<p>1) Vertical tongue position. Vowels can be low, mid, or high.</p>

<p>2) Horizontal tongue position. Vowels can be front, mid, or back.</p>

<p>3) Lip position. Vowels can be made with rounded lips, neutral lips, or spread lips.</p>

<p>4) Vowel length. Vowels can be short or wrong.</p>

<h4 id="now-why-is-this-nonsense">Now, Why Is This Nonsense?</h4>

<p>Vowels aren’t static. They’re not made in the same way across all languages. (Almost) Every language has a version of /p t k/. But even in languages with THE SAME vowels, they might be said differently. In people who speak the same language or even the same regional dialect, vowels can be said differently.</p>

<p>Vowels themselves and the phonemes that mark them aren’t absolutes. They’re signifiers for a sound that’s in an acceptable range of sound quality.</p>

<p>Look at the nonsense that <strong>formant charts</strong> are if you want to see how difficult it can be to distinguish different vowels.</p>

<p>An addendum: there are even more distinguishing features for vowels, such as the mystifying <em>tense</em> and <em>lax</em>, and adding diphthongs to the mix makes all of this even more muddied.</p>

<h4 id="one-more-ridiculous-example">One More Ridiculous Example</h4>

<p>English is not a language that distinguishes between long and short vowels phonemically. Thai is. However, English <strong>pronunciation</strong> has sneaky phonological rules regarding vowel length. In general, vowels followed by a voiced consonant are longer than vowels followed by a voiceless consonant. Say the following pair of words a few times, playing around with the vowel length.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[hi:t] <em>heat</em> and [hIt] <em>hit</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Notice how <strong>heat</strong> is much longer than <strong>hit</strong>? and if you make one too long and the other too short it’s much harder to tell the difference? Welcome to reason 83209 why English is such a hard 2nd language to learn. Even when my students are pronouncing (mostly) the word-final consonants in “crab” and “crap”, because of the vowel length, the words are often indistinguishable.</p>

<p><em>Of course, they rarely pronounce the -b and -p correctly anyway, since word-final consonants are usually devoiced or elided in Thai, and -b and -p aren’t phonemically separate. Hooray English.</em></p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>What is a Consonant Though?</title>
	  <link>//what-is-a-consonant-though</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-22T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//what-is-a-consonant-though</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="definition-problems">Definition Problems</h2>

<p>There are two definitions for “consonant”, and they both come with their own problems.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Definition one: sounds made by restricting or blocking the airflow in some physical way.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem with this definition is that it leaves out the English phonemes /j/ and /w/, which can be found in words like <u>y</u>ard and <u>w</u>ish, respectively. /j/ and /w/ have tongue positions and are semi-vowels/glides as opposed to proper consonants. Which means we have to bring in another way to distinguish them from vowels.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Definition two: a sound that either alone or in a consonant cluster marks the beginning or end of a syllable.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This makes a lot of sense, because those with Linguistics training know that the vowel is the heart of the syllable. They know that consonants can only start or end syllables, and they know that there is a finite number of consonant clusters and variations that can occur at the beginning or end of any given syllable.</p>

<p>Great! Although:</p>

<p>Unless you’ve HAD a bunch of Linguistics training, you don’t know what sounds ARE allowed to be the beginning/ending of syllables. English has a lot of weird rules.</p>

<p>For instance, we have the voiced velar nasal -ng word finally but not word-initially. That’s not a universal thing, there are plenty of words in Thai that start with ng-. Snake, for example, is ngoo.</p>

<p>We can begin a syllable with str-, spr-, sl-, tr-, and many other two-or-three consonant clusters. But unless you take the time to think about it, this isn’t a very helpful way to determine where the consonants and vowels are.</p>

<p>What I would suggest if I was teaching non-linguists is to say that <strong>a consonant is any sound that constricts or stops the airflow in speech OR is /w/ or /j/</strong>.</p>

<p>If I was teaching linguists, I would love to go into syllable restraints, stress, vowels, syllabified consonants, and all that fun stuff. But in general, the people I teach are small enough to still get to have naptime after lunch.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Sa-now, Teacher. Sa-now</title>
	  <link>//snow-teach-snow</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-20T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//snow-teach-snow</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="krashens-natural-approach-and-affective-filter-hypothesis">Krashen’s Natural Approach and Affective Filter Hypothesis</h2>

<p>i.e. why we don’t teach “mittens” to Thai children.</p>

<p>It doesn’t matter a single bit if material is “authentic” or “artificial”: a map of the London Underground is just as “real” to a Thai child as a dialogue from Gilligan’s Island. In order for language to be authentic, it should be <strong>applicable</strong>.</p>

<p>We teach “mangosteen”, “rambutan”, and “durian” far before we teach “peach” “pear” or “fig”, simply because a Thai child might not have ever seen a peach, and will either way be more likely to shout the English word of a fruit he or she sees every day as opposed to a few times on a flash card.</p>

<p>The affective Filter Hypothesis expands on this and states that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“input is more likely to become intake if learners feel good, about themselves, about the target language, and about the learning environment. Furthermore… although increasing the stress on students in class may improve their short-term learning, it has negative effects on their long-term acquisition.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In our practice, we sort of trick the students into learning. It’s the old “hide the pill in the hot dog” trick, which is especially effective for young learners. More broadly, however, it can be applied to almost all the language teaching that we do. A learner that feels confident in their speaking ability, who is praised and given constructive criticism, will not only seek out more opportunities to speak but will actually <strong>learn faster</strong>.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>The Problem with 3rd Person 'S'</title>
	  <link>//the-problem-with-s</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-18T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//the-problem-with-s</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="why-does-3rd-person--s-take-so-long-to-stick">Why Does 3rd-Person -s Take So Long To Stick?</h2>

<p>3rd-Person -s is taught early and drilled often in an ESL classroom.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Suzy run<strong>s</strong>”</p>

  <p>“We run”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It is a simple rule that can be easily understood. And yet it is often and repeatedly forgotten by students, even at a high level.</p>

<p>Here’s the answer:</p>

<h3 id="it-serves-no-real-purpose">It serves no real purpose.</h3>

<p>It is a redundant morphological function. We already know whether or not the subject of a verb is plural by the other components of the sentence - the subject itself, the subject pronouns, and sometimes words in the predicate.</p>

<p>While it is morphologically important, it is not semantically significant.</p>

<p>Again I say “Take that, Chomsky”.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Sentence Constituents</title>
	  <link>//sentence-constituents</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-14T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//sentence-constituents</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p><strong>Clauses</strong> are a thing. We’re not talking about them yet.</p>

<p><strong>Basically</strong> we try to organize information from the beginning to the end. While we don’t have topic markers, it can be assumed in English that the first part of the sentence is common knowledge or is at least setting the listener up to hear new information.</p>

<h2 id="types-of-constituents">Types of Constituents</h2>

<p>1) <strong>Noun phrases</strong> - consist of a noun or an article/adjective noun, or even a relative clause, but in general are all about a single thing. ex) the dog that bit me, a really old car.</p>

<p>2) <strong>Verb phrases</strong> - the same but for verbs. don’t recommend staying, goes with.</p>

<p>3) <strong>preposition phrases</strong> - begin with a preposition and then contain a noun phrase. On the corner, with many additional features.</p>

<p>4) <strong>adjective phrase</strong> - contain an adjective, which can follow one or more adverbs,</p>

<p>5) <strong>Adverb phrases</strong> - contain an adverb which can also follow MORE ADVERBS</p>

<h2 id="functions">Functions</h2>

<p>1) <strong>Subjects</strong></p>

<p>2) <strong>Direct Objects</strong></p>

<p>3) <strong>Complements</strong> - usually tell us something about the subject. Could be a noun phrase, adjective phrase, preposition phrase, or another clause. She became <u>a nicer person</u>. Complement verbs usually don’t make sense on their own (was, become).</p>

<p>4) <strong>Indirect Objects</strong>  - don’t forget double object stuff also. This all makes sense to me because Spanish conveniently marks all of its objects and object pronouns. Apparently it might be easier to teach some indirect objects as adverbials. “she told the truth <u>to her husband</u>.”</p>

<p>WTF is the difference between objects and complements? We can distinguish them in terms of meaning. Objects refer to different things than subjects. Complements refer back to the subject.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“She bought a car.”</p>

  <p>“She became a celebrity.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The first has an object, the second has a complement. Another good test is that sentences with objects can be restructured into the passive voice and sentences with complements cannot.</p>

<p>5) <strong>Adverbials</strong> are apparently a mystery. They can be PP, AdvP, or NP and usually begin with a preposition. They’re optional information we can add to a clause, and we can string a bunch together. They could also be an entire clause. Good.</p>

<p>6) <strong>Coordinating Conjunctions</strong> what’s your function? Hookin’ up words and phrases and clauses. And but or.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Now they tell me. Sentences consist of a subject and a predicate. Predicates can be verb phrases, indirect objects, direct objects, double objects, or complements. All of this can also be based on the type of verb we choose, which are eponymous to the predicate type.</p>

<hr />

<h2 id="extra-bits">Extra Bits</h2>

<p><strong>Dummy subjects</strong> are like null subjects or the null letter in thai. They don’t contribute to the meaning, but they are necessary for syntax. Take that, Chomsky. “It’s raining.”</p>

<p><strong>Hay</strong> is its own grammatical construction in English - “there is”/”there are”. They don’t follow any other rules and are confusing.</p>

<p><strong>Separated verb phrases</strong> are a thing we do sometimes.</p>

<p><strong>Spoken English</strong> changes all these rules based on the whims of its mercurial speakers. Another problem for teachers and the model/real speech gap. See <u>On Model Speech.</u></p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Assumptions About Input</title>
	  <link>//assumptions-about-input</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-14T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//assumptions-about-input</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="two-central---and-erroneous---assumptions">Two Central - and Erroneous - Assumptions</h2>

<p>According to The Lexical Approach, there are two central assumptions about language learning that have been disproven with actual research.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“a. It is possible (and desirable) to sequence language.”</p>

  <p>“b. Learning is a step-by-step process, and too much input would confuse.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Obviously this is wrong. Primary language acquisition isn’t done in careful steps - babies are essentially bombarded with all aspects of a language at once. We do use “motherese” when speaking directly to babies, but we don’t use it anytime a baby can hear us. The television certainly isn’t only speaking in “motherese” either. We also don’t try to shut up around the baby for fear it may become overwhelmed by the language. On the contrary, we speak to it as much as possible. We describe our activities. We name literally everything the baby sees or tries to put in its mouth. And we absolutely know they’re not going to retain all that - yet we don’t dilute the flow of language.</p>

<p>So too is immersion school thought to be the best tool for secondary language acquisition. “Go to a foreign country and you’ll pick up the language so much more quickly!” And yet in a regular language classroom, we are wary to carefully space out grammar and vocabulary and concepts, lets we overwhelm the learners.</p>

<p>This is something I have found myself guilty of in my own classrooms - if a lesson is focused around a particular theme, I often won’t dump a lot more out-of-theme language into it. I have seen kids retain information from the densest of sessions, and also be unable to recall one of the only four vocabulary words they learned in a previous session.</p>

<p>Clearly this should influence my practices, and it’s fascinating to read the theory behind this. The question lies somewhere in the middle, of course. Not all input will be valuable to the learner, so how do we distinguish useful input from extra noise?</p>

<p>There are some factors we cannot control for, of course - they reside in the mindset of the learner. Attention span, tiredness, interest level, motivation, etc.</p>

<p>What we can control:</p>

<p>a) <strong>input should be comprehensible</strong></p>

<p>b) <strong>input should relate in some way to what is already known and expand upon it</strong> (for a good example of this see the Pimmsler tapes and their rather steep learning curve)</p>

<h2 id="in-conclusion">In Conclusion</h2>

<p>Language should be “roughly tuned” to the needs of the learners. The message should be understandable, and the language used should be below, at, and slightly above the comprehension of the learner. According to Krashen,</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Language acquisition can only take place when a message which is being transmitted is understood, i.e. when the focus is on what is being said rather than the form of the message. This could be referred to as the <strong>Great Paradox of Language Teaching</strong>.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Is it paradoxical at all? It makes sense to this teacher that language that is useful and interesting is language that is easier to acquire.</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Transitive Verbs Take an Object</title>
	  <link>//transitive-verbs-take-an-object</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-12T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//transitive-verbs-take-an-object</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>Intransitive verbs do not.</p>

<p>That is all.</p>

<p>Let this be the last time I confuse transitive and intransitive verbs.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Dichotomies Involved in Language Teaching Part 2</title>
	  <link>//dichotomies-in-language-teaching-part-2</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-10T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//dichotomies-in-language-teaching-part-2</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <ol>
  <li><strong>Signification and Value</strong> - Signification expresses the contextless meaning of a word, such as its dictionary definition. “This is my hand” is meaningful as a sentence but meaningless as an utterance - it takes a little bit of creative thinking to imagine this said in a normal conversation. But signification exists, sicne pictionary as a game works. We can have contextless meaning. Value is metaphorical meaning, omitted words that are understandable in the context of a conversation, or pronouns with agreed-upon meaning. Continues with the distinction of “correct” and “successful” language, or the further ideas of grammatical or communicative competence. See <strong>On Model Speech</strong>.</li>
  <li><strong>Cohesion and Coherence</strong> - Cohesion is the grammatical linking of one part to another. It can be exemplified (but is not always so explicit) by repetitions of similar grammar or lexis across sentence boundaries, or in the case of conversation, across turn boundaries. Coherence is how a conversation remains structured without directe grammatical links, but rhetorical and situational ones instead. “Cohesion is about grammatical linking, coherence about pragmatic linking”.</li>
  <li><strong>The Classroom and the Real World</strong> - This whole section is a sort of survey of the different models/approaches of language teaching, a lot of which can be summed up in this category, or at the very least have been brought into focus as this category has become more important in the discourse. While it’s awesome that we have the tools to study real speech increasingly and with greater volume, unanalyzed natural speech should be neither the target nor the model for classroom speech. In the past, the gulf between the classroom and the real world was too great. We don’t want to combine the two, but real speech should be both acknowledged and given more significance in the classroom. Although the classroom is not the “real” world per se, it is a situated activity system in that while all participants are there and interacting, it is <strong>a</strong> real world. There’s a risk in only being exposed to classroom speech, but there’s an equal risk in only being exposed to “real” speech, as your vocabulary/semiotics would be extremely diminished.
    <ul>
      <li>“The Lexical Approach suggests that much greater emphasis needs to be placed on students’ building a large vocabulary much m ore quickly than in any traditional syllabus.” Some of those words will have to be devoid of context - i.e. using flash cards and realia to tie words to meaning, but not introducing them in a sentence every single time with a purpose.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Product and Process</strong> - A product is any language which a student creates, and products are created as a result of processes. Process is a developing, dynamic concept, which contrasts with the static nature of product. Teachers are necessarily product-oriented, because we have to have some way of evaluating processes. Thus essays, tests, etc. It is important to remember the processes involved in creating these products, though.</li>
  <li><strong>Accuracy and Fluency</strong> - usually for describing two different kinds of exercise. Accuracy demands that a student get the language “right”. Fluency exercises tend to be more open-ended, and ask for a demonstration that the student be able to use the language, not just recognize the correct usage. The Lexical Approach holds that fluency leads to accuracy, as opposed to the other way around.
    <ul>
      <li>“Despite the obvious fact that accuracy is a late-acquired feature of all language learning, it remains regrettably true that many teachers emphasize accuracy too early, and at the expense of fluency.”</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Learning and Acquisition</strong> - Both used to describe how we learn languages. Acquision is the internalization of rules and formulae which are then used to communicate but for this purpose counts as “the spontaneous process of rule internalisation that results from natural language use, while ‘learning’ consists of the development of concsious knowledge through formal study”. Sure. According to this theory, we are able to test learning but not acquisition. It’s obvious that we do both of these things, but we should not think that they’re entirely unconnected.</li>
</ol>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
