<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>adventuresinteach.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://www.adventuresinteach.com/</link>
   <description></description>
   <language>en-uk </language>
   <managingEditor> Jaqueline Steiger</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Word Nerding Out</title>
	  <link>//word-nerding-out</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-04T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//word-nerding-out</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>My newest textbook is “The Lexical Approach” and its core principle is here: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<strong>The lexical approach</strong> is a method of teaching foreign languages described by Michael Lewis in the early 1990s. The basic concept on which this <strong>approach</strong>rests is the idea that an important part of learning a language consists of being able to understand and produce <strong>lexical</strong> phrases as chunks.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So it’s bottom-up as opposed to top-down and is sort of how my program that I’m in approaches ESL teaching. I’m INTERESTED, but I’m not already drinking the Kool-Aid yet. I was definitely p-type and not s-type in school, but there’s also only so much communicative competence you can demonstrate by shouting individual words in random orders. </p>

<p>Interested in hearing what other word nerds think about the Lexical Approach, since I never read it in undergrad. Maybe @dedalvs?</p>

<h4 id="some-context">Some Context</h4>

<p>I’m starting the DELTA, which is a post-grad program for teaching ESL teachers. Eventually I want to set up a TEFL school - not to teach children English, but to teach the teachers HOW to teach children English, and this is the certification I need to do that.</p>

<h5 id="even-more-context">Even More Context</h5>

<p>I actually don’t start DELTA Module 1 until September 12th. Why am I reading the textbooks a month in advance? Because I have a full-time job and another part time job and the course supposedly adds 15-20 hours of work a week to my 40-hour-a-week teaching job and my 15-hour-a-week remot production coordinating job. I want to get the jump on these textbooks so that I don’t succumb to exhaustion like an old-school lady protagonist.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
