<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
   
      <title>adventuresinteach.com/</title>
   
   <link>http://www.adventuresinteach.com/</link>
   <description></description>
   <language>en-uk </language>
   <managingEditor> Jaqueline Steiger</managingEditor>
   <atom:link href="rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
   
	<item>
	  <title>Discourse Markers</title>
	  <link>//discourse-markers</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-28T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//discourse-markers</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h3 id="meta-language">Meta-language</h3>

<p>We have a whole secret category of words that don’t have any semantic meaning. They don’t add to the sentence, they don’t impart any specific meaning regarding the intent of the speaker or writer. The only thing they do is provide information about the STRUCTURE of the sentence/phrase/speech (utterance) itself. We call these <strong>discourse markers</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="what-do-discourse-markers-do">What Do Discourse Markers Do?</h3>

<p>They help us organize the flow of information. We can use them to:</p>

<p>1) Signpost logical relationships and sequences - “firstly” “furthermore”, etc</p>

<p>2) Manage conversation and turn-takeing - “and you?”</p>

<p>3) Influence how our listeners or readers react - “all the same”</p>

<p>4) Express our attitude to what we say and write - “I’m afraid”</p>

<p>This is really more of a feeling than a hard and fast category. There’s not a whole lot of consensus or rigidly-defined list of discourse markers. Here are some examples:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Firstly</p>

  <p>in fact</p>

  <p>on the contrary</p>

  <p>however</p>

  <p>nevertheless</p>

  <p>futhermore</p>

  <p>right?</p>

  <p>you know</p>

  <p>on the other hand</p>

  <p>so</p>

  <p>anyway</p>

  <p>uhh</p>

  <p>finally</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All of these words/utterances tell us information about the discourse preceding or following it. How does it relate? Where is it in a sequence? How do we feel about it?</p>

<p>Things that discourse markers can do:</p>

<p>a) numbering and order</p>

<p>b) adding something</p>

<p>c) linking similar things together</p>

<p>d) introducing something that contrasts with expectations</p>

<p>e) causes and results</p>

<p>f) generalizing</p>

<p>g) exemplifying and narrowing down</p>

<p>h) re-stating</p>

<p>i) rounding off</p>

<p>j) conversation management</p>

<p>How do we teach something as subjective, varied, and intricate as discourse markers?</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Classifying Consonants</title>
	  <link>//classifying-consonants</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-26T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//classifying-consonants</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="how-do-we-distinguish-consonants">How Do We Distinguish Consonants?</h2>

<h3 id="voicing">Voicing</h3>

<p>Consonants can either be voiced or voiceless, and English comes with paired voiced and voiceless consonants: /p/ <strong>/b/</strong>, /t/ <strong>/d/</strong>, /k/ <strong>/g/</strong>, etc.</p>

<p>Note that English does not distinguish between aspirated and unaspirated consonants (<strong>aspirated</strong> = a puff of air accompanies the sound as it comes out of your mouth. Put your hand up to your mouth and say “pot” and “spot”. You’ll feel air come out for “pot” but not “spot”) but many other languages do.</p>

<h3 id="place-of-articulation">Place of Articulation</h3>

<p>We talk about consonants based on where in the mouth the airflow is restricted. Consonants that involve the lips are <em>labial</em> or <em>bilabial</em>. Consonants that involve a curled-back tongue are <em>retroflex</em>.</p>

<p>Generally, the places of articulation (FOR ENGLISH) as we move back through the mouth are thus: bilabial, labiodental, alveolar, alveopalatal, velar, glottal.</p>

<p>Fascinating types of sound we don’t have in English: retroflex, palatal, uvular, pharyngeal.</p>

<h3 id="manner-of-articulation">Manner of Articulation</h3>

<p>This variable describes the <em>way</em> in which airflow is constricted.</p>

<p><u>Stops</u> or <u>plosives</u> involve a complete blockage of airflow.</p>

<p><u>Fricatives</u> involve a narrowing of the airways and generally a hissing sound.</p>

<p><u>Nasals</u> involve air moving through the nose as well as the mouth.</p>

<p>There’s a lot of types, some of them are really interesting!</p>


	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>What is a Consonant Though?</title>
	  <link>//what-is-a-consonant-though</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-22T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//what-is-a-consonant-though</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <h2 id="definition-problems">Definition Problems</h2>

<p>There are two definitions for “consonant”, and they both come with their own problems.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Definition one: sounds made by restricting or blocking the airflow in some physical way.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The problem with this definition is that it leaves out the English phonemes /j/ and /w/, which can be found in words like <u>y</u>ard and <u>w</u>ish, respectively. /j/ and /w/ have tongue positions and are semi-vowels/glides as opposed to proper consonants. Which means we have to bring in another way to distinguish them from vowels.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Definition two: a sound that either alone or in a consonant cluster marks the beginning or end of a syllable.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This makes a lot of sense, because those with Linguistics training know that the vowel is the heart of the syllable. They know that consonants can only start or end syllables, and they know that there is a finite number of consonant clusters and variations that can occur at the beginning or end of any given syllable.</p>

<p>Great! Although:</p>

<p>Unless you’ve HAD a bunch of Linguistics training, you don’t know what sounds ARE allowed to be the beginning/ending of syllables. English has a lot of weird rules.</p>

<p>For instance, we have the voiced velar nasal -ng word finally but not word-initially. That’s not a universal thing, there are plenty of words in Thai that start with ng-. Snake, for example, is ngoo.</p>

<p>We can begin a syllable with str-, spr-, sl-, tr-, and many other two-or-three consonant clusters. But unless you take the time to think about it, this isn’t a very helpful way to determine where the consonants and vowels are.</p>

<p>What I would suggest if I was teaching non-linguists is to say that <strong>a consonant is any sound that constricts or stops the airflow in speech OR is /w/ or /j/</strong>.</p>

<p>If I was teaching linguists, I would love to go into syllable restraints, stress, vowels, syllabified consonants, and all that fun stuff. But in general, the people I teach are small enough to still get to have naptime after lunch.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>

	<item>
	  <title>Word Nerding Out</title>
	  <link>//word-nerding-out</link>
	  <author>Jaqueline Steiger</author>
	  <pubDate>2016-08-04T00:00:00+07:00</pubDate>
	  <guid>//word-nerding-out</guid>
	  <description><![CDATA[
	     <p>My newest textbook is “The Lexical Approach” and its core principle is here: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“<strong>The lexical approach</strong> is a method of teaching foreign languages described by Michael Lewis in the early 1990s. The basic concept on which this <strong>approach</strong>rests is the idea that an important part of learning a language consists of being able to understand and produce <strong>lexical</strong> phrases as chunks.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>So it’s bottom-up as opposed to top-down and is sort of how my program that I’m in approaches ESL teaching. I’m INTERESTED, but I’m not already drinking the Kool-Aid yet. I was definitely p-type and not s-type in school, but there’s also only so much communicative competence you can demonstrate by shouting individual words in random orders. </p>

<p>Interested in hearing what other word nerds think about the Lexical Approach, since I never read it in undergrad. Maybe @dedalvs?</p>

<h4 id="some-context">Some Context</h4>

<p>I’m starting the DELTA, which is a post-grad program for teaching ESL teachers. Eventually I want to set up a TEFL school - not to teach children English, but to teach the teachers HOW to teach children English, and this is the certification I need to do that.</p>

<h5 id="even-more-context">Even More Context</h5>

<p>I actually don’t start DELTA Module 1 until September 12th. Why am I reading the textbooks a month in advance? Because I have a full-time job and another part time job and the course supposedly adds 15-20 hours of work a week to my 40-hour-a-week teaching job and my 15-hour-a-week remot production coordinating job. I want to get the jump on these textbooks so that I don’t succumb to exhaustion like an old-school lady protagonist.</p>

	  ]]></description>
	</item>


</channel>
</rss>
